<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sommons to doomes daie sent vnto his beloved England, as a memoriall of his deepe printed loue and loyaltie.  / By Henoch Clapham..</title>
            <author>Clapham, Henoch.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07516</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 76698316</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5345.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91454</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">76698316</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 76698316</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184223</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07516)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184223)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 2241:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sommons to doomes daie sent vnto his beloved England, as a memoriall of his deepe printed loue and loyaltie.  / By Henoch Clapham..</title>
                  <author>Clapham, Henoch.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Robert Walde-graue, Printer to the Kings Majestie.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1595..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border; head-piece, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁸.</note>
                  <note>"Cum Priuilegio Regio." -- at foot of t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in: Peterborough Cathedral.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 2nd, III, 10-11 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184223:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184223:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOMMONS TO Doomes daie</p>
            <p>SENT VNTO HIS BELOVED ENGLAND, AS A ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of his deepe printed Loue and Loyaltie.</p>
            <p>By HENOCH CLAPHAM.</p>
            <p>EDINBVRGH PRINTED BY RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Walde-graue, Printer to the Kings Majeſtie. An. 1595.</p>
            <p>Cum Priuilegio Regio.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:184223:2"/>
            <head>SCHOLASTICIS.</head>
            <p>LArgè ſpatiari, Rhetoris eſt; ſtrictè au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Dialectici. Hoc proprium Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum Scholis: illud, Roſtris. Medium inter vtrunque, hoc potius (vt ἔυαγγελὶας, Prophetae accommodatius) hic ſtudui. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neae ſi quae occurrunt otioſae (error verò hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus ſaeculi loquacis, maximè fluitans) illas ego repudio nec probo. Facilius autem eſt deſtruere, quam aſtruere: nec difficilius la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beculae non ſerpente connivere, quàm labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum labem (vt nè dicam luem) in aliorum lucubrationes, evomere. Quid tum peto? vt aequo (ſi non placido) legatis animo; vel ſaltem pacato, haec mea qualiacun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis: hoc ſummiſſè petitur ac flagito, </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete.</salute> 
               <signed>H. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:184223:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>WEET <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> wiſhing all true happines to thee and my ſoueraigne Queene <hi>ELI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>TH,</hi> (whoſe bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>erſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries inteſtine a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rane, God in due time convert or confounde) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vrged to voyage from thee for a ſeaſon, I haue heere commended vnto thy reading, this mite of a mountaine of Good will. Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warning, is a fore-arming, neither will my ſommoning thy ſoule (howſoeuer harſhe at firſt) proue otherwiſe than healthfull at laſt. Some in whome is ſmall good Zeal but more malice, will (conſidering my perſon) wring what ſences they liſt from my ſentences, that ſo they may ſnarle behinde my back: But let ſuch learne, that <hi>Loue will judge the beſt, but Malice never ſpake well.</hi> Some in whome Zeale overmatcheth knowledge, will <hi>è contra</hi> affirme, that I haue not plainlye
<pb facs="tcp:184223:3"/>ynough rebuked ſinne, &amp;c. Let ſuch learne, that I haue learned, that there is one man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Rebuke in the Church of the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, another Rule in the Church of the newe Teſtament: one maner of dealing with perſons within the viſible Church, another wiſedome towardes them that are without. He that followes one rule for forme of rebuke may aſwell confound the firſt and latter mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie. This not obſerued cauſeth much tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, but no good done. <hi>Wordes vttered according to knowledge diſcretiue,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 25.11</note> 
               <hi>are like apples of golde &amp; pictures of ſilver.</hi> Accept it with no worſe meaning than I offer it, then neither ſhalt thou diſdaine to receiue it, nor I repent the guift: and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching the Lordes bleſsing to accompanie my labour, I end. <hi>Edinburgh, 1595.</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <hi>Fulgura ſic flammas qui terris ſervat iniquis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anglorum Sωter ſemper, vbique ſiet.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy humble petitioner vnto God for thy good. <hi>HENOCH CLAPHAM.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:184223:3"/>
            <head>SOMMONS TO DOOMES-DAIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. PET. 3. verſ. 10.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="10">10 But the day of the Lord wil come as a Theefe in the night, in the which the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ſhall paſſe away with a noiſe, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements ſhall melt with heat, and the Earth with the vvorkes that are therein, ſhall bee burnt vp.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 Seeing therefore, that all theſe things muſt be diſſolued, what maner perſons ought ye to be, in holy converſation and godlines.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holy Apoſtle PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER, writing vnto all whereſoever, that had obtained the like preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous faith, even the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious faith of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, doth vnto all (and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnto vs, if wee be Chriſtians) deliuer
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184223:4"/>many ſaving doctrines and wholeſome exhortations grounded vpon their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, for the further confirmation of faith and increaſment of ſanctification. Amongſt which, this one (namly a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat and warning peale of the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole worlde by fire, and the great day of Doome) is not leaſt vrged, but of all the reſt moſt forciblie in this Chapter propounded and preſſed, and eſpecially in theſe two verſes now read. Before the handling of which two ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, it ſhall be vnto me neither grievous, nor to you vnprofitable, that I ſumme vp the precedents of the chapter. In the two firſt verſes, the bleſſed Apoſtle, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vp the Readers of his Epiſtle, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the enſuing doctrine into the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of their mindes, (for indeede a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt minde will but mock there at) and the rather they are mooved therevnto, becauſe the doctrine ſhould be no newe or ſtrange doctrine, but even ſuch a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as before had bin delivered: Firſt by the holy Prophets, ſecondly by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184223:4"/>Apoſtles of our Lord &amp; Saviour: which doctrine he calleth a Commandement, becauſe it was not a leſſon left, to learne or beleeue at a chriſtians leaſure or ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but enjoyned vpon every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans neck, by the holy Prophets before Chriſt came, by the bleſſed Apoſtles af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt come: a commaundement to the Church of the old Teſtament, and a commaundement to the Church of the newe Teſtament: and therefore not ſuch a leſſon as may be beleeved and vnbele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, received and refuſed at mens plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: but a commaundement ſent vnto all that ſtudy puritie of minde, and do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waite the comming of our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>In the thirde and fourth verſes, hee foretels the pure minded of certaine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries to the ſaide doctrine: and this he doth, firſt by ſetting down their time of ariſing: namely, <hi>In the latter daies:</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by giuing vnto them an Epithet drawn from the qualitie of their ſpeach, vz. <hi>Mockers:</hi> thirdly, ſetting downe a <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſis</hi> or <hi>compendium</hi> of their ſpeache,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184223:5"/>which is this: <hi>Where is the promiſe of his comming? for ſince the Fathers died, all things continue alike from the beginning of the Creation:</hi> as though they ſhould ſay, <hi>You write and you talke of Chriſts comming vnto Iudgement, ſaying, that there ſhall bee an end of all theſe worldly thinges: I cannot tell, the old ancient Fathers they died and ſo do we die, others came in their roomes, and ſo doth there in ours and not onely that, but ſuch creatures as were then, ſuch are nowe, daies, moneths and years turne about, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and comming againe in a worde, I ſee nothing changed, but all things alike now as of old, and therfore I cannot beleeue that the ſaying (The World ſhall bee conſumed, and the Chriſt ſhall come vnto Iudgment) that it is any thing elſe, but a tale of <hi>Robin-hood,</hi> and therefore I will walke on in the waies of mine owne heart, and in the delight of mine owne eies, making my heauen heere whileſt I liue heere: for after death, I cannot beleeue there is any account no nor life, no more then of a dead Dog, and pitted caryon.</hi> All theſe and ſuch like blaſphemies, the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184223:5"/>accompts no better than a <hi>Mock,</hi> and the perſons themſelues <hi>Mockers,</hi> namely, of God and his word. In the 5. and 6. verſes, the Apoſtle rendreth a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their <hi>Atheiſme &amp; Infidelitie:</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they are <hi>willingly ignorant,</hi> of what? <hi>That they are willingly ignorant how the heauens had their beeing by the word of the Lord,</hi> (for they think the Heavens to come of themſelues) <hi>as alſo ignorant howe the earth by the ſame word of</hi> ELOHIM <hi>was ſeparate from the waters and had his foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſaith) <hi>laid vpon the waters:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 24.2.</note> 
               <hi>and therefore by the ſame worde of God brought aboue the Earth, what time the old world was deſtroyed by water.</hi> This I take to bee the true ſence of them two verſes. In the ſeventh verſe, he teacheth the pure minded, that the ſame worde that brought forth the former effects, the ſame worde is the preſeruer of the Heauens and Earth, during the time of their conſervation: but that the ſame word hath determined an end vnto the Heauens and the Earth, which ſhall as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184223:6"/>verely take place by fire (as erſt by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) The day of which deſtruction ſhal be, what time the Lord ſhall vtterlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye the vngodly: cloſely intimating thus much: <hi>As the waters overflowed the Earth,</hi> in that day wherein God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to preſerue <hi>Noah</hi> and to deſtroy the vnbeleevers: ſo verely ſhall the fire ceaze vppon the Heavens and Earth in that day, wherein our God hath ſecretly concluded the deſtruction of all ſuch mockers and vngodlie perſons.</p>
            <p>In the eight and ninth verſes, hee ſtirreth vp the beloued of the Lord to be grounded in a perſwaſion quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto the former mockers: Firſt, in not being ignorant, as the former were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie ignorant: Secondly, to teſtifie their not being ignorant by beleeving, firſt, that before the Lord, <hi>one day and a thouſand yeares are alike;</hi> (this is ſecretlie oppoſed to the ignorant judgement of the mockers, who thought God woulde neuer come, becauſe hee had driven ſo many yeares) Secondly, by beleeuing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184223:6"/>that the Lord will not be ſlack in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his promiſe of comming, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſome in their fooliſhnes accounted him ſlack: for the effecting of which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe in them, hee giueth in the next words a reaſon (not of the Lords ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but) of his not deſtroying the world and comming vnto judgement, <hi>as yet:</hi> namely, becauſe he hath decreed a time, wherein (with all long ſuffering) he will awaite the repentance of people, that ſo they might be ſaued: This ſecretly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuateth thus much: Euen as the Lord, (before he would deſtroy the old world by water) did with loue and much pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence even an
<note n="*" place="margin">Geneſ 6.3. 1. Pet. 3.20.</note> hundred &amp; twenty years, awaite the repentance of the people: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo with patience and aſmuch (ey more) lenitie, he now awaiteth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of people from <hi>Sinne</hi> to <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> that ſo in that great and fearfull day, they might bee ſaved, and not with the vngodly be deſtroied.</p>
            <p>Now come we to the text read: wherin is conſidered two things; Firſt, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184223:7"/>of the doctrine generall in the firſt verſe read, by a ſimple affirmatiue: Secondly, by way of conceſſion in the firſt clauſe of the next verſe: then an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, vrged by an interrogation in the next and laſt clauſe. In the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion generall, wee haue to obſerue the comming of the Lord in theſe wordes: <hi>But the day of the Lord will come:</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the manner of his comming, <hi>like a Theef in the night:</hi> Thirdly, what ſhall be effected by his comming, vz. <hi>the paſſing away of the Heuens, with the Elements mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting:</hi> Secondly, of the Earth, by the <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of fire:</hi> Thirdly, the conceſſion of the whole in theſe words: <hi>Seeing all theſe things muſt be diſſolued.</hi> The exhortation included in the interrogation, lieth in theſe wordes, <hi>What maner of perſons ought ye to be in holy converſation and godlineſſe?</hi> The comming of the Lord, expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>But the day of the Lord vvill come,</hi> is an oppoſition to the mockers ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatiue axiome which was this: <hi>The day of the Lord vvill not come.</hi> And to make
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184223:7"/>the affirmation more forcible, the holy Apoſtle preponeth the particle, <hi>But:</hi> as though he ſhuld ſay, <hi>You mockers affirme that the Lord vvill not come, But I affirme he vvill come.</hi> Thus the Apoſtles of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and the Apoſtles of Chriſt, will be ever in contradictions, like to IEHOVAH and Satan in Paradiſe, The Lord he ſaid, <hi>In eating of the tree of knowledge of good &amp; evill, thou ſhalt dy the death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 2.19.</note> Sathan ſoone after ſaide,
<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall not die at all.</hi> The impes of Satan can ſay, <hi>Loe all things in the world are as they were woont to be, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God will not come to iudgment:</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of IESVS he ſaith, <hi>But the day of the Lord will come.</hi> Whether nowe ſhall we beleeue? the abhominable Atheiſt, or the bleſſed Apoſtle PETER? To the wicked their <hi>fore-but,</hi> the Apoſtle oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his <hi>But:</hi> which <hi>But,</hi> will prooue ſo mighty a wal in the end, as neither moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers nor mockers diſciple, ſhall be able to leape over without breaking the neck of their ſoule. The Apoſtle PAVL, hee plainely ſaith to the Theſſalonians,
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.2</note> 
               <hi>Ye
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184223:8"/>knowe perfectly that the day of the Lordſhal come:</hi> but our Mockers ſay, <hi>vve knowe perfectly that the day of the Lord ſhall not come.</hi> Holy IVDE bringeth in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of
<note n="*" place="margin">Iude. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>Henoch,</hi> ſaying, that <hi>the Lord commeth vvith thouſandes of Saintes to giue iudgment:</hi> And our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe affirmeth
<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 24.</note> that <hi>Hee will come with the ſounde of a Trumpet::</hi> but our Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds affirme, that all theſe things are but tales and deviſes of men: whom ſhal we beleeue now? The bleſſed Apoſtles, and our Saviour himſelfe: or theſe birds of the bottomles pit, that breath blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie againſt God and his worde? A wonder of the worlde, that man ſhould be ſo infatuate and ſenſles. But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle a little before giues the reaſon here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: namely, that they willingly are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, howe the Lord by his word hath made and conſerved the Heauens and Earth, as alſo howe heretofore by the ſame potent word, hee brought the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vpon the Earth to the deſtruction of all Creatures breathing, excepting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184223:8"/>them in the Arke. Theſe Atheiſts, blind Moles, are ignorant of the Worde and works of God, ey willingly ignorant, elſe they could not but knowe that the Lord will come vnto judgment. Let the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt mocking Atheiſt anſwere to this queſtion: <hi>Is there not ſometimes a qualme comming over thine heart, when thou mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreiſt, vvhen thou ſteales, vvhen thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits adulterie, &amp;c. Feeleſt thou not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a griping of thy Conſcience,</hi> Speake plaine, ly not? Oh yes thou Atheiſt! thou art not ever exempted from ſuch nips, girds and cold qualmes. What meanes thine hart to admit of ſuch moleſtures? Oh thou Atheiſt, thy ſoule is affraid and trembles to come before one, that will take an accompt of thy wicked life: that will judge that ſinne, and plague it with Hell fire. Thy Conſcience therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth thee: thy ſoule trembles with thy Predeceſſor <hi>Diagoras,</hi> neither ſhalt thou eſcape the Iudge before whom thy ſoul ſo citeth and ſommoneth thee.
<note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 14.13</note> Euen in laughing thine heart is ſomtimes ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184223:9"/>and the end of thy mirth attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with heavines. Put the evill day farre from thee for a while, yet the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof, wil ſomtimes croſſe thy banquet: when thou art ſo overthwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, imagine thy ſelfe to bee
<note n="*" place="margin">2. King 21.20</note> 
               <hi>Ahab,</hi> and that overthwarter to be <hi>Elijah.</hi> Say vnto the twitching light of thy Conſcience, <hi>Haſt thou found me, oh mine Enemie?</hi> and it ſhall anſwer, <hi>I haue found thee, for thou haſt ſold thy ſelfe to worke wickednes in the ſight of the Lord:</hi> when the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>But the day of the Lord will come,</hi> he wold oppoſe that <hi>Day,</hi> vnto the daye of the wicked. The wicked now haue <hi>their</hi> day; the Lord then wil haue <hi>his</hi> day: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that great day is called the Lords day. Chriſt his reſurrection day, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the
<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Lords day,</hi> becauſe hee then tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed over the Deuill, death and ſin: ſo this day of Doome, is called the Lords day; becauſe hee then will for ever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Deuill, and thoſe that haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in the waies of death and ſinne, to everlaſting torture. As ABRAHAM
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184223:9"/>could equally conclude againſt DIVES, <hi>Thou hadſt then thy pleaſure, and</hi> Lazarus his torment; therefore now it is juſt, that thou bee tormented and <hi>Lazarus</hi> haue pleaſure: ſo againſt all wicked ones, I conclude; <hi>As you haue your day nowe, ſo Chriſt ſhall haue his day then:</hi> walke on in the waies of your own fleſh, but be ſure, the day wil come that ſhal pay for al. In this day the wicked ſhall cry, Hilles and mountaines fall vpon vs, and cover vs from him that ſitteth vpon the throane: but as for the godly, let them hold vppe their heades, for then is come the fulnes of their redemption. Woe be vnto theſe that nowe laugh (becauſe of ſin) for then they ſhall mourne, but bleſſed be theſe that now mourne (becauſe of ſinne) for they then ſhall laugh and be comforted. This day of the Lord (ſaith PETER) <hi>ſhall come,</hi> as though hee ſhould ſay, tremble oh wicked man, for thy day of judgment ſhall come: be patient and rejoice, thou that art perſecuted for righteouſnes ſake for the daye of judging thy cauſe ſhall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184223:10"/>come. This daye is figured out by the Prophet
<note n="*" place="margin">Ioel. 3.12 14.</note> IOEL, vnder IEHOVAH, his pleading in the Valley of <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> in the daye of his threſhing the Heathen. Howſoeuer the Lord ſeeme now to be a ſleepe (the wicked thinking God like to themſelues) yet then the Lord ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake as a Gyant refreſhed with wine,
<note place="margin">Pfal. 50.21</note> &amp; bring them vnder the cruſhing blowe of his flayle, a flayle of judgment that ſhall beat them like chaffe: In the meane time let all knowe, that whatſoever <hi>Mockers</hi> ſay, <hi>The day of the Lord ſhall come.</hi> Iudge righteouſlie (oh yee rulers of the Earth) preferre not the cauſe of the Potent to the cauſe of Widowes and Orphanes: ſlaughter not Chriſt in <hi>Habell,</hi> commit not
<note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 22.27.</note> 
               <hi>Michajah</hi> (with <hi>Ahab</hi>) vnto priſon, nor dare to feed the Lords Prophet with the bread and water of affliction, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter yee haue had your daies of judging and pleading, the Lords day ſhall come, wherein hee will examine the cauſe of the poore and oppreſſed. If yee haue not judged and done according to God his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184223:10"/>book, but according to the inequall bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of your owne making, then hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. 10.1.</note> ISAIAH, <hi>Woe vnto them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree wicked decrees, and doe vvrite grievous things, for keeping back the poor from Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for taking away the iudgment of the poore of my people, that Widowes may be their pray, and that they may ſpoile the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe. What will yee do now in the day of viſitation &amp; of deſtruction, which ſhal come from farre? to vvhome will ye flie for helpe? and where will ye leaue your glory?</hi> Oh yee Rulers of the Earth, <hi>The day of the Lord ſhal come</hi> as verely as the <hi>Aſſirians, Medes-Perſians, Graecians, Syri-Egyptians,</hi> vpon <hi>Iudah:</hi> your judgments ſhall bee weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ballances of the Sanctuarie: if they be found faithfull and full weight, then enter into the poſſeſſion of glorie: but if they be found partial and too light with <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> kingdome, then thou ſhalt be caſt out for counterfeit coyne. If oh yee widowes, fatherles and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſtreſſed ones, ye here in the day of man cannot be equally dealt withall, do
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184223:11"/>not curſe, murmure, but reſt patient for a while,
<note place="margin">Revel. 6.9.</note> (as vnder the bloody Alter <hi>Ieſus,</hi> more injured than thou) and after man hath had his day of playing <hi>Rex jex, The day of the Lord ſhall come,</hi> what time the Lord will examine their Law-books by his ſacred Teſtament, and call back the examination of thy cauſe in the hearing of men, angels and devils. Looſers muſt haue their ſayings, and the wicked their wordes for a ſeaſon: but <hi>The day of the Lord ſhall come,</hi> wherein they ſhall bee forced to ſtand by, and to hearken what the Lord ſhall ſay. Ieſus himſelfe was here, of the Rulers &amp; Prieſts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſcarſelie vſed as a <hi>Lord,</hi> nay, vſed like a traytor to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> like a ſower of ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doctrine, like a ſuperſtitious conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; in a worde, like an of skouring of the world, even as are his members: but in this day hee will come as a LORD, to whome al power in Heauen and Earth is given, and they ſhall looke vpon him and his members myſtical, whome they haue pearced. In the day of this life they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184223:11"/>would dominere, and Lord it over him and his: but now ſhall he and his Lord it over them. In this day of the Lord, <hi>Habel</hi> ſhal Lord it over <hi>Cain:</hi> the
<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 2.</note> ſlaughtered infants, over the Fox <hi>Herod, Lazarus</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Dives:</hi> In this day, the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> ſhal awake the mocking Atheiſt, and let him knowe, that there is a God that judgeth the earth. The workers of iniquitie, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their preaching and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Devils) ſhall this day bee dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the ſocietie of the faithfull and the face of Ieſus. Now, the Lord wil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, how they haue
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 25.24</note> fed and clothed the poore: viſited the priſoner, and been mercifull vnto the diſtreſſed. They ſhall in this day (even every lippe-goſpeller) know what difference there is betwixt a dead faith, or idle beleefe not working: and a liuely Faith that bringeth foorth fruites of righteouſnes and holineſſe. If they will not here in this life
<note n="*" place="margin">Iam. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>ſhewe their faith</hi> (which is inviſible) <hi>by holy vvorkes,</hi> (which are viſible) then fear in that gret daye of our Lord to heare the ſentence,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:184223:12"/>
               <hi>Depart from mee yee curſed into everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.41.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, this ſhall bee a day of feare, and horrour: Our Lord ſhall bee vnto the wicked and vngodly, the roaring Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Iudah:</hi> but vnto the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full members of IESVS, it ſhall be a day of ſolace and glorie: for vnto them, ſhall Chriſt be the meeke Lamb ſlaine from the beginning of the Worlde, wiping away all teares from their eies: ſetting them on his throane, even as himſelfe nowe ſitteth on his Fathers throane, &amp; ſo aeternize their felicitie vnto them; for that ſhall be the <hi>Lords day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, who will not beg with <hi>Lazarus</hi> now, that he may glorie with <hi>Lazarus</hi> then? who wil not now lay down the life of his bodie for an houre, that ſo he may receiue of the Lord then, life for yeares, millions of yeares, even for aeternitie of time beyond al time? On the other ſide, who will bee ſo madde, to murther with <hi>Cain</hi> heere, for ſatisfying a ſodaine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaine luſt, and then bee damned to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184223:12"/>the pit of torment for ever? who will be ſo mad, as for ſparing a little meate and drinke, with the proud glutton from the needie, to ſell his body and ſoule to the Devill, and the damnable pit for ever? Oh fooliſh and vntoward fleſhe of ours, that remembers not this day, this feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day, to the workers of vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. It is written of a certaine Ancient, that he ſo lived, as ever opening his eare, and liſtening vnto the voice of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels trumpet that ſhuld cry, <hi>Come, come away vnto Iudgment.</hi> If we would ſo liue, as ever liſtening after the appearance of the Lord in this his day, then aſſuredlie, wee would not dare to ruſh into adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſtealth, and other prophaneſſes as we doe. When thou art tempted to defile thy Neighbours bed, to filtch away thy Neighbours goods, to impriſon or kill the innocent, &amp;c. Then ſay thus within thy ſelfe: Oh miſerable man, nowe the ſpirite of Hell with the bellowes of his malice, is blowing and puffing vppe thy luſtes to ſette them on fire, that ſo thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184223:13"/>members may commit iniquitie: this Sathan doeth, to haue me damned with him: If I followe the motion of this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpirit, what gaine ſhal I therby win? I ſhall ſatisfie my luſt of vncleannes, of filching, of wrath, of pride: Oh, but God hath damned that luſt, and ſet his curſe vpon that work: what if the terrible day of the Lord come, as I am committing that ſinne? or if not, howe ſhall I exſpect Gods mercie vnto repentance after the doing of the ſinne, that knowes before hand, that it is diſpleſing vnto my God? what is an howres pleſure to fierie tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments induring for ever? why ſhould I grieue God, and cauſe the Devill to bee merrie? thogh the great day of the Lord come not vppon me at this inſtant, yet this day may be the day of my death, &amp; then commeth my ſoules Iudgement: ſhall I then hazard my ſoule, nay, ſhal I wittinglie commit it to the Devils ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, who is deſirous to drawe me with himſelf vnto the black burning pit? Thus debate with thy ſelfe, then tell mee what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184223:13"/>pleaſure thou canſt take in ſinning? Oh Lord, ſweet Lord Ieſus! though this ſhal be a terrible day to the Atheiſt, mocker, and counterfeit Chriſtian, whoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure then endeth, and whoſe endles pain and torture then beginneth: yet vnto thy poore afflicted ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, it ſhal be a day of glee and gladnes, for then ſhall their dolour end, and their never fading glorie beginne: then ſhall the wicked be tormented in hell fire: but thy people ſhall raigne in the beauteous heavens, then ſhall the wicked be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled and chained with the Devill and his Angels, in the Iron bandes of thy wrath: but thy ſanctified members ſhall be
<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>like thee,</hi> ſee thee as thou art, &amp; wait vpon thee (the Lambe) whither ſoever thou goeſt. Sweete Ieſus, ſanctifie the conſideration heereof vnto thy people, that by the torture of the wicked, &amp; the glorie of the godlie, they may be drawn from ſinne to ſerue thee in righteouſnes and holines all the daies of their life.</p>
            <p>But how ſhall this day come? The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184223:14"/>hauing learned that, of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus, what time hee preached vnto them the deſtruction
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> doth anſwer: <hi>it ſhal come as a theefe in the night,</hi> that is, even as the theefe ſtealeth vpon a man in the night ſeaſon, vnawares to the houſholder, even in the time of his ſleepe; ſo ſhall this day of the Lord vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares and ſudenly, come vpon the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the earth: ey, our Saviour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Lukes</hi> rehearſall ſaith, that this day, ſhall as a
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 21.35</note> 
               <hi>ſnare</hi> come on all them that dwell vppon the face of the whole earth, that is, even as the beaſt or bird not thinking of any danger neer, is then vnawares caught in a ſnare: ſo ſhall the dwellers on the earth, ſodainly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out foreknowledge, be arreſted by the day of the Lord. Methinks to him that is content but to vnderſtand according to ſobrietie:
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.3</note> another queſtion (and that a curious one) is heerein anſwered. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny demaund in what daye or in what yeare, <hi>This great day of the Lord ſhall fall?</hi> Of the houre and daye, no profeſſor of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184223:14"/>Chriſt dare define, becauſe our Saviour hath ſaid plainlie,
<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 24.36.</note> 
               <hi>Of that day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, but my Father only:</hi> but concerning the yeare ſome dare determine: for ſay they, though the houre and day be not reveiled in the word, yet the year is clear lie vnderſtood from <hi>Daniel 12. &amp;c.</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (ſay they) let it be marveled, that the yeare ſhould be pointed at, conſidering the Devils had ſome foreknowledge of that time when they cried,
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 8.29.</note> 
               <hi>Art thou come hither to torment vs before our time?</hi> As alſo <hi>Elias</hi> plainlie fore-propheſied: <hi>The World ſhall ſtand ſix thouſand yeares, and then it ſhal be conſumed with fire.</hi> And having determined the vttermoſt day to fall out <hi>Anno 1700.</hi> they then qualifie their judgment by ſaying,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1700"/> that ſomthing of theſe times muſt be cut off, from <hi>Mat. 24.22. &amp;c.</hi> To anſwer to all theſe things at large, would require a peculiar trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: and it is bruited (but I knowe it not of certaintie) that
<note n="*" place="margin">L. Chad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derton, M. of that Colledge</note> one of <hi>Immanuel</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> hath publikelie there confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184223:15"/>the opinion, I therefore as I ſpeak of it but by the way, will therefore but by the way ſhape foorth this litle anſwere. The ſhortning of the daies, <hi>Matth. 24.22.</hi> is properlie ſpoken of the cutting of them troublous daies of miſerie, which came vpon <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> what time the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes beſieged it. This may bee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from our Saviours words in the 15.16.17.18.19.20.21. verſes aforego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The people there are willed for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding them troubles, to flee out of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea.</hi> If them daies were ment of the daies immediatelie before the ending of the world, to what end ſhould hee ſpeake of flying out of <hi>Iudea?</hi> to what end ſhould he will the people to make ſuch haſte in flying from houſe and ſubſtance? and howe ſhould it then bee better for ſuch women as were not with child, then for theſe that were, except he ment, that the firſt might with leſſe paine and trouble flie away from the ſworde of Titus and his ſouldiers, as alſo from the ſworde of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Read <hi>Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus de bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, Iud.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Divided</hi> in the Citie? why ſhould
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184223:15"/>he wiſh them to pray that theſe troubles might befall <hi>Iudea</hi> in the ſommer, rather than in the winter, but that hee knewe that ſnowe and foule weather wold hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpeedines of their flight. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, to cauſe our Saviour in DANIEL, to giue foorth a limited yeare, and then in the time of his fleſhe, to cut ſomewhat from that time, even 12. yeares, as ſome haue, is to make Chriſt yea and nay, which the Apoſtle PAVLE denieth, 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1.19.20. as alſo a breaker of the Prophets, which himſelfe denieth. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17. Them troublous daies there ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of (and it is affirmed, verſe 22. of them that they ſhould be ſhortened) can not bee ſpoken of the laſt troubleſome times, that ſhall come vppon the whole world.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Elias</hi> prophecie, (which may bee numbred amongſt the Papiſtes vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten verities) I ſay no more but this: <hi>I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him not for</hi> Elijath <hi>the</hi> Tiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite: <hi>for his Canonicall ſpeaches are regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by the holy Ghoſt in the book of Kings,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:184223:16"/>neither haue wee any ſuch ſpeach there or elſe where, in the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as is this.</p>
            <p>As for the Devils, they might well ſay, that the <hi>latter</hi> day was not yet come, wherein they ſhould begin to bee more notablie tormented, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be far ynough from foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Latter day.</hi> The Devill had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the prophecies of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that there ſhould bee a long di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betwixt the incarnation of Chriſt and the end of all things. He knewe that Chriſt muſt haue his ſpirituall poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſtreatch over
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 2.8.</note> the Heathen, vnto the corners of the Earth. As yet the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition wall was not broken downe: and after the lawe ſhould go out from <hi>Zion</hi> to the Gentiles, there would bee ſome yeares ſpent for gathering the Heathen vnto the faith of Chriſt. Beſides, <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 59.20.</note> had prophecied an vniverſall calling of the Iewes (which time as yet is vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired) and from many other circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces every where in the Prophets, the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:184223:16"/>devils might eaſilie know, that the time of Chriſt his incarnation could at noe hand be the time of the Lords laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, namely, to judgment. That ſpeach therefore of the Devils, is nothing to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>As for the numbers, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.11.12. which ſome would haue (as to be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares, ſo) to be accompted from <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the Apoſtates time <hi>An</hi> 365. what time it is ſaid,
<note n="*" place="margin">Carion, Chron. lib. 3.</note> that he in ſpite of Chriſt commanded the <hi>Iewes</hi> to build the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which afterwardes was by thunder and earthquake overturned to the cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> and ſo accounting from that time, would haue the world to ceaſe at fardeſt in the latter number, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.12. Thereto I anſwer: If it were the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels meaning there, to ſpeake of the end of this world, I could not but reverence that conjecturall beginning of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt: but as the ſpirite of God in the greateſt viſions, as of that of the 4. met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, and the other of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 2. Cap. 7. Cap. 11.</note> 4. beaſtes, as alſo in the <hi>Revele</hi> of the <hi>Syrian</hi> and <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:184223:17"/>actes (their Kings tearmed, King of the <hi>North,</hi> King of the <hi>South</hi>) as in all theſe, the Lord leadeth <hi>Daniel,</hi> not to the conſideration of the ſtate of the newe Teſtaments Church, (except vnder type or figure) but for the comforting of him and the Iewes, doeth foretell vnto them the ſtate of the Church of the Iewes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the kingdomes of <hi>Chaldea, Mede-Perſe, Grecia, Syri-Egypt,</hi> and that vntill the comming of Chriſt in the fleſh, and the
<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 9.24</note> ſealing vp of <hi>(the old Teſtaments)</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and prophecie. ſo I cannot eaſilie conſent vnto the former conjecture, but reſt in this judgment; namely, that them daies, <hi>Dan. 12.11.12.</hi> were properlie gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen forth for the Iews to accompt, what time their
<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 7.8. &amp;c. and 11 36. compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red with 2. Theſ. 2.3.4.</note> notable Antichriſt of <hi>Gogs</hi> land (the figure of our Sonne of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſhould tread them and their temple vnder-foote.</p>
            <p>And whereas they think, that the age of theſe laſt times, (by reaſon God is one and the ſame) ſhould no more bee hid to the faithfull nowe, then was the date of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184223:17"/>the firſt world vnto <hi>Noah,</hi> I anſwere: God is one and the ſame, though hee reveale not the thinges whereof wee haue no promiſe, as alſo not like need, as had <hi>Noah,</hi> who was during that <hi>120.</hi> yeares, to prepare an Arke for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the ſecond world. Secondly, if the knowledge ſhuld be proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, then all the faithfull muſt know <hi>This,</hi> for ſo no doubt the faithfull then with <hi>Noah</hi> vnderſtoode <hi>that.</hi> Againe, the very yeare, ey the day ſhould bee knowne of <hi>This:</hi> for ſo was
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 6.3 &amp; 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>That.</hi> But the day, our Saviour plainely denieth, (doth he therefore <hi>Repent his goodneſſe towards the faithfull?</hi>) and themſelues giue it 12. years compaſſe to fal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, (vz. betweene 1588. and 1700.) themſelues therfore conclude againſt themſelues.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſee not why from this ſpeach of <hi>Peter, The day of the Lord ſhal come as a Theefe,</hi> as alſo that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaith it ſhall come <hi>as a ſnare,</hi> that is, <hi>vnawares,</hi> and that not onely vpon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184223:18"/>ſome, but <hi>vpon all that dwell vpon the Earth</hi> I ſee not (I ſay) why I may not from this forme of ſpeach conclude, that noe probable conjecture of the year may be giuen. And whereas they affirme, that though the Day bee not knowne, yet the yeare may be known: I anſwer, firſt, I ſee no ſuch thing from the Scriptures alleadged: Secondly, where our Saviour denieth the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of the <hi>Day,</hi> I ſee not why by <hi>Day</hi> may not (ey, muſt not) be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood <hi>Time,</hi> indefinitely, as though he ſhould ſay: <hi>That time is vnknown to the ſonne of man:</hi> even as when he ſaith, <hi>The houſholder would watch, if hee knewe the Time.</hi> The faithfull all know, that that day will come, and therefore doe watch over their waies: ſo that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it ſhal come, it ſnal
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.4</note> not come vnlooked for: &amp; yet our Saviour ſaith, it ſhall come vnlooked for as a theefe. This then muſt neceſſarilie bee our Lord and Maſter his meaning: <hi>Watch and be ye ſober,</hi> (ſpeaking to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184223:18"/>in their perſons) <hi>that ſo that great day (in regard of limitation comming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares vppon you) may not in regard of your beleeuing and wayting for the ſame, ſteale on you as on the wicked.</hi> This take I to be the very natiue ſenſe of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and his Apoſtles wordes and allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: from all which I conclude, that I ſee not howe from Scripture, the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite time of our Lords comming to judgment can be gathered.</p>
            <p>Many having in their mouthes, in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> his time,
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.3</note> 
               <hi>That the day of the Lord was at hand,</hi> hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore amongſt other things, writ vnto the Saints at <hi>Theſſalonia</hi> (where chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie this was bruited) that it was falſe: becauſe, before that great day of the Lord, there ſhould be a <hi>Departure,</hi> (or generall Apoſtacie from the faith of Chriſt) a thing taught by <hi>Iohn</hi> in his <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> where hee ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>Heauen,</hi> (not a part of Heaven: neither are we ignorant, howe the Church is called <hi>Heauen</hi> in all that book, as alſo, <hi>Mat.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184223:19"/>11.11. &amp; 13. &amp;c.) Heauen</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted away as a ſcrole when it is rolled.</hi> Secondly, (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) before that day of Chriſt, the man of ſinne ſhall bee
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>diſcloſed:</hi> Thirdly, he ſhall be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: (and therefore called the Sonne of perdition)
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> by the ſpirit of Chriſts mouth: namely, in the powerfull mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of his word: Chriſt then (as he rid on with <hi>Salomon, Pſalm. 45.4.</hi> vpon the white Horſe in the
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 6.2.</note> firſt ſeales o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening, namely, vppon the worde of truth, meeknes, and righteouſnes) ſo ſhall hee returne for the perdition of the Antichriſtian body, vpon the ſame worde or
<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 19.11. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>white Horſe</hi> iſſuing out of Heaven <hi>(the Church)</hi> then opening, and the armies of faithfull iſſuing foorth with him, for the deſtruction of the Gentiles, the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> the earthly Kings, falſe Prophetes, and Idolatrous mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked People. At the perimpliſhment whereof, I look for the generall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> prophecied plainely of by <hi>Iſaiah, (59.20. &amp; 60.)</hi> by <hi>Zechariah,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184223:19"/>(12.10. &amp;c.)</hi> by <hi>Paule (Rom. 11.25.26.)</hi> and the glory of their Church figured out plainlie, <hi>Revel. 21.</hi> compared with <hi>Iſaiah, 60.</hi> All which well waighed, ſome may ſay: <hi>Many things fore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied of, and yet vnfulfilled, are to fall out before that day, therefore not like it is at hand:</hi> I anſwere, how things are ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected abroad in the world, I nor thou wholie vnderſtand: Secondly, I feare that the multitude of the worlde will not perceiue theſe effects, nor acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge the holy Church, but rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe with weapons to aſſiſt
<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 20.7. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> againſt the Church, till fire come downe from heauen &amp; devoure them. Thirdly, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> not ignorant of the former prophecies, did notwithſtanding in his time crye out, <hi>The day of the Lord is at hand, (1. Epiſt. 4.7.)</hi> teaching vs, ſo to fix our eye on this great day, as no numbers of yeares foregoing, may be deemed a day, in compariſon of that eternitie of time that then beginneth. This
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184223:20"/>
               <hi>Time</hi> finite and endable: that infinite and without end, as to the elect ſaved, ſo to the reprobate damned: as alſo, to ſtirre vs vp to account of Time, as God accompteth time: that is, future time to be preſent before our eies, the glaſſe of time runne, the Iudge at the doore, and therefore accordingly to prepare our ſelues to judgment: This neceſſarilie by the way, now to the vſe of the doctrine.</p>
            <p>Will the day of the Lord come as a theefe, even then when all the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the earth ſhall no more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne the time, then did <hi>Sodome, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrha, Zeboim, Admah,</hi> the fire and ſulphure rained downe vppon them? Oh how had wee neede to watch, and
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 21.34</note> to take heede to our ſelues, (as our Saviour admoniſheth) leſt at any time our hearts be oppreſſed with ſurfeting drunkennes, and cares of this life, leſt that day come vpon vs vnawares? how had we need to
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> watch and pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie, that wee may bee compted
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:184223:20"/>worthie to eſcape al theſe things, that then ſhall come to paſſe, and that wee may ſtand before the Sonne of man? If a ſervant knew that his Lord at ſuch a time would come, he would happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie within that time, orderly diſpoſe of all things: but alaſſe, we are ignorant of the time of our Lords repaire. Sure we are he wil come, but how ſodainly we know not, except even then, when we leaſt dreame of his comming.</p>
            <p>If any man ſay, tuſh, tuſh, the day of the Lord is not neere, I anſwere: but thou knows that thy day is neere. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the <hi>Great day</hi> be farre of, yet thy death-day is not farre off. What leaſe haſt thou of thy life but till to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe? and when thou art dead, all the world is dead with thee. As thou falls, ſo receiues thy ſoule judgment. Haue thou bene never ſo righteous, if thou be cut downe in ſinne vnrepented off,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> all thy former righteouſnes ſhall be forgotten: thou ſhalt vntill the greate day of the Lord, be chained in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184223:21"/>of horrour, where the vnfaithfull and diſobedient to
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.19</note> 
               <hi>Noahs</hi> preaching are ſtil pent: &amp; in that general doome the body ſhall be vnited with his ſoul, and as they ſinned togeather, ſo liue a never dying death togeather. Let not the Devill therefore ſounde in thine cares, the day of the Lord is nor neere wherein all ſouls ſhall be judged, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering there is a day neere, wherein thy ſoule ſhall be judged. Death may as ſuddenly arreſt thee vnto this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular doome or <hi>Fore-ſeſsion,</hi> as fire ſhall ſommon the whole world vnto that generall <hi>Aſſiſes</hi> and Iudgment. He that now ſaith, <hi>Heart be at reſt,</hi> may by and by heare: <hi>Oh Ideot, this night they ſhall take away thy ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Noah</hi> preached the end of all fleſh, they eat, drank, married, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, planted, ſported out the daye, and ſlept out the night: but then, even then, the <hi>Cataracts</hi> of Heaven burſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and the waters belowe mounted aboue their bounds, ſwelling till they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:184223:21"/>overpeered the higheſt mountaines, &amp; ſuffocated all fleſh, excepting them in <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke: when with the fat fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Boare, and rainging Heifer, they deemed themſelues moſt happy, even then they became haples and accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. With the faithfull, <hi>Sorrowe is ouer night and ioy in the morning:</hi> but with the prophane and vnbeleever, <hi>Ioye is ouer night, and ſorrowe in the morning:</hi> Feare, feare &amp; tremble then, oh thou Earthworme, who ſavours nothing but earth and duſt, as doth the ſerpent who was appointed to
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 3.14.</note> glide on the earth, and to feede on duſt. <hi>Salomon</hi> knew it a
<note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 28.14.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed thing alwaies to feare,</hi> and art thou wiſer, in thinking thy ſelf bleſſed, living <hi>feareleſſe?</hi> As the lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning flaſhing ſodainely from Eaſt to weſt, ſo ſhall the comming of the Son of man be. Outward conjectures may bee drawne of his neere approching, (as is, <hi>Faith liuely,</hi> hard to bee founde: <hi>Coldnes of loue, vnnaturalitie, &amp;c.</hi>) but the <hi>period of time,</hi> (be it day, moneth,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:184223:22"/>yeare) as vncertaine, as is the day, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, yeare of the theeues aſſailment vnto the houſholder.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> As wiſe houſnol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders therefore, haue we alwaies ready the helmet of <hi>Saluation,</hi> not of <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> the breſtplate of <hi>Righteouſnes,</hi> not of <hi>Iniuſtice:</hi> the girdle of <hi>Truth,</hi> not of <hi>Falſhood:</hi> the ſheild of <hi>Faith,</hi> not of <hi>Vnbeliefe:</hi> the ſword of the <hi>Spirite,</hi> not of the <hi>Fleſh:</hi> ſhooes prepared to carrie vs to <hi>Vtter forth,</hi> and to <hi>heare</hi> the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of peace: not to carrie vs from <hi>vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering</hi> and <hi>hearing</hi> he peaceable Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: and aboue all other things, let vs <hi>Alwaies pray,</hi> that come the <hi>Day gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> or <hi>particular,</hi> wee may be founde well exerciſed: that when the wicked ſhal yell and roare, and crie out to the mountaines to cover them, then wee may with comfort lift vp our heades, becauſe that is the daye of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Apoſtle wel knew, that the bare and naked ſaying, <hi>The day of the Lord will come ſodainlie,</hi> wold
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:184223:22"/>ſmallie availe to rowſe vp perſons ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted vnto the things of the worlde; hee in the next place joineth with his comming ſuch an effect, as happilie may cauſe churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> to tremble: <hi>The Heauens</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſhall paſſe away with an hiſsing noiſe, the Elements ſhall looſe with heate, and the Earth vvith the works therein ſhall be burnt vp.</hi> Heere <hi>(ſed pace Doctorum dixerim)</hi> by <hi>Heauens</hi> I vnderſtand the celeſtiall globes of the ſeaven planeticall or wandering Starres, together with the firmamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſphere and firſt <hi>Moouer,</hi> as alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exteriour circles (if any ſuch be) beyond our ſight, and probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture. By the (στοιχεια) <hi>Elements,</hi> I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand according to the nature of the word, the Elements of <hi>Fire, Aire, Earth, water,</hi> whereof other creatures haue their conſtitution: all which, by that <hi>Iudiciall heate ſhall be looſed</hi> By the <hi>Earth and works therein,</hi> I vnderſtand the groſſe corrupt commixture of the Earth, together with the edifices and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:184223:23"/>other workes of men remaining vpon the corrupt compoſition of the earth: for otherwiſe, every <hi>Scholler</hi> knoweth, that the Elements are eſſences &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances <hi>ſimple, ſingle,</hi> as is the ſpirite of man.</p>
            <p>That the Heavens are ſaide to paſſe away with an <hi>hiſsing noiſe,</hi> he would teach, that in that great daye, the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall ſpheres, ſhal depart or giue place with an hiſsing, as doeth a ſcroule of parchment having received fire. This ſenſe is probable from the forme of ſpeach vſed by <hi>Iohn,</hi> where hee ſaith,
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>The Heauens departed as a ſcroule when it is rolled.</hi> I well vnderſtand, that <hi>Iohn</hi> there ſpeaketh of an other Heauen; namely, of the heavenlie places of the Saintes, and viſible face of the true Chriſtian Church, making as <hi>Paule</hi> faith,
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>A departure:</hi> but as for the phraſe or forme of ſpeache, it is bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from this effect, as though hee ſhould ſay, <hi>The face of the myſticall Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> (the Church) <hi>ſhall ſo depart from his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184223:23"/>former outſtretched viſibilitie, as ſhall the materiall Heauens at laſt, when they ſhall role away together.</hi> As this by the way giveth a gird vnto theſe that pleade a perpetuall outſtreatched viſibilitie of the Church: ſo it plainlie pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, that the ſuperiour heavens ſhall once (even in the day of the Lord) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and run together as a ſcroll. That it is ſaide, <hi>The Elements ſhall melt</hi> (or bee looſed) <hi>vvith heat</hi> (or as they doe heate) I know not what, but this ſhuld be meant: namely, that the Elements and ſimple ſubſtances (who nowe are commixt and poſſeſſed with corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſhall then bee looſed (as pure ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is melted) from their commixture, droſſe and corruption, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlie be reſtored into their firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie and libertie: ſeeing this is the end of their groaning <hi>Rom. 8.19.20.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh thou Churle that nowe cries, <hi>Heart be at reſt:</hi> and oh thou Harlot, that ſaieſt with <hi>Babell,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. 47.10.</note> 
               <hi>I am and none
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:184223:24"/>elſe:</hi> what wilt thou do when the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens rattle, the Elements melte, the Earth and all earthly things are ſet on flame? flie out of the Citie, the fire is in the fieldes: run out of <hi>Iudea,</hi> the fire is in <hi>Syria:</hi> climbe <hi>Nimrods</hi> Towre, &amp; ſulphure from Heaven powres down vpon thee: skulpe in the cavernes of the earth, and the earth it ſelfe falls on burning like a barrel of pitch: deſcend into the Seas, and the water is vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through heat. Nowe <hi>Cain,</hi> the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie builder, ſhall ſee his Cittie on fire: <hi>Abſaloms</hi> Piller ſhall frye, and hee that intytleth his houſe by his name, ſhall in this great daye ſee it whollie on a flame. Oh <hi>London, London,</hi> and oh ye her ſiſter Citties, in this great daye of the Lord (if ſo the Lord meet not with you before) what ſhal become of your golden ſhewes in your ſhops? What (in this daye) ſhall become of your ſumpteous ward-robes? what ſhal then become of the rentalls &amp; debtbooks? Surely, this deſtinate fire ſhall pay all
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:184223:24"/>debts. All theſe earthly works ſhall be ſet on flame: and in a moment and trice, all ſhall be conſumed, for which all haue cared, and ſome conſumed themſelues. The King as poore as the peſant: and the meaneſt Cobler equal with <hi>Caeſar.</hi> If thou wilt hardly giue credence to me, enquire of <hi>Diues</hi> (that hauing paſſed the <hi>Seſsion,</hi> awayteth with horrour the generall <hi>Aſsiſes</hi>) and hee will tell thee, that his back and his ſoft rayment, his bellie and his daintie fare, haue made an everlaſting par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: <hi>Lazarus</hi> as rich as himſelfe: nay, as riche and bleſſed in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aboue, by reaſon of faith: as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is beggerlie and accurſed, (not worth a drop of cold water) lodged in the Devils boſome belowe, by reaſon he had no faith; at leaſt no liuely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king faith. The miſerable Churle in the Goſpell, having filled his barnes, ſate downe, ſaying, <hi>Nowe ſoule reſt thee;</hi> but immediatlie, hee heard from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen this ſpeach; <hi>Thou foole, this night
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:184223:25"/>they ſhall take away thy ſoule.</hi> Thus a fool and his ſubſtance were quicklie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and when hee dreamed his ſoule ſhuld be at moſt reſt, then it was vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie divorced from reſt. And if before the great day of the Lord, we ſee even every daye, that worldlings and the world are ſundred, &amp; al they take with them to be but a winding ſheet: what ſhall we think of this great day of fire, devouring vnmercifull fire, that will not leaue ſo much as a winding ſheet vnburnt to aſhes? when the Heavens ſhal depart with hiſsing, the Elements diſſolue, the Earth and his workes be ſet on fierie flame: what ſhall become of the gods of the Heathen, and of our Romiſh <hi>halfe-gods</hi> and <hi>halfe-goddeſſes,</hi> made of gold, ſilver, bone, ſtone? will they then for the <hi>Popes</hi> ſake eſcape this devouring fire?
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 31.34</note> 
               <hi>Rahel</hi> vnder the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of a foule diſeaſe could cover her pretty gods from <hi>Labans</hi> eies: But in this great daye, who will cover their painted, enoyled ſhrines? no, curſed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:184223:25"/>ſhall be both Image and Image-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, howſoever now they are tearmed <hi>Lay-mens books:</hi> yet in that great day, it ſhall appeare true,
<note place="margin">Habak. 2.18.</note> that <hi>Habakkuk</hi> long ſince writ, namely, that <hi>they are but teachers of lies.</hi> Oh day of horrour, oh thou day of feare and trembling, oh that man is forgetfull of thee: now purſuing egerlie after worldly traſh &amp; vanitie: all which, in that great daye ſhal be turned into aſhes. Gold, ſilver, pretious ſtone, trees, plants, hearbes, flowers, ſtraw, dyrt, dunge, all ſhall be jumbled togeather, all wrapped vp in one: for this is a fire of wrath and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. All which well waighed, what marvell was it, that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhuld crie out:
<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Vanitie of vanities, Vanitie of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, all is but vanitie.</hi> When the fire ſhall cauſe all the glory of this worlde to <hi>vaniſh,</hi> no marvel if it be called, <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie:</hi> moſt vaine then is man, that ſells his ſoule and bodye to the Deuill for Vanitie.</p>
            <p>Heere it will be demanded, <hi>If ſo the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:184223:26"/>faithfull ſhall together with the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full frye in this fire?</hi> thereto I anſwere: when the floodes of wrath came vpon the old worlde, then was <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke: when fire and brimſtone rayned downe on the Citties of the plaine,
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 19.22</note> then was LOT in <hi>Zoar:</hi> this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therfore, is thus anſwered by Saint PAVL vnto the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> (1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 4. Chapter, verſe 17. <hi>Theſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine liuing, and theſe that ariſe from ſleepe,</hi> (namelie, from the graue) <hi>ſhal be together caught vp in the clowdes, to meet the Lord in the ayre.</hi> As the waters of deludge ceazed on the diſobedientſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, not on <hi>Noah:</hi> as the fire and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phure faſtened on the carkaſes of theſe that vexed the ſpirit of <hi>Lot,</hi> not on <hi>Lot</hi> himſelfe: ſo this <hi>Fire of wrath,</hi> (not of <hi>Correction</hi>) ſhall parche the bodies of the wicked, not of the Lordes people. As the faithfull that carrie heere the Croſſe of IESVS on their ſhoulders, may heereby receiue juſt occaſion of comfort and rejoicing: ſo, theeues, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:184223:26"/>murderers, witches, all that loue lies and vnrighteouſnes, may bee ſmitten downe and not haue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to be ſolaced. After this daye, (the greate daye of deliverance) ſaith PAVL,
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Wee groane that haue the firſt fruites of the Spirite:</hi> Theſe that nowe groane not for this day, as for the day of gaole deliverie; they ſhall groane in that day, as being the day of fearefull captivitie. That gret day (oh my God) thou knowes I long after: looking for litle reſt till that day, but after that day deſireth not the man, that hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the earneſt pennie of thy ſpirit: for here is his <hi>Heauen,</hi> neither doth he exſpect any good in that great day of fire. Oh my God, cauſe me to be ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſo ſtronglie, with the memoriall of that daye, (as alwaies <hi>preſent to my eyes</hi>) as I may not dare at any hand to ceaſe preaching thy ſacred worde, nor for any worldlie maintenance to bee drawne to conceale any trueth from thy people, Amen.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:184223:27"/>
            <p>After this day of deliverie, groane not onely wee that haue the firſt fruits of the ſpirit, (and the firſt fruits ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the whole lumpe, <hi>Rom. 11.16.</hi>) but ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle,
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.21 22. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (whether having onely <hi>being;</hi> or <hi>being</hi> and <hi>moouing:</hi> or <hi>being, moouing,</hi> and <hi>ſence:) every of them groane togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvith vs, and traueleth in paine for the preſence of this great day, that ſo they</hi> (as well as wee) <hi>may bee delivered from their bondage of corruption.</hi> As by our ſinne they became corrupted (and ſo ſubject to rottennes, ſtench, impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp;c.) falling togeather with vs, ſo they ſhall riſe and recover their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, glorious eſtate, but not till the day of our deliverance, and therefore introduced groning togither with the Faithfull after the <hi>Laſt day.</hi> As theſe creatures (after a ſort) do groane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burden of our ſin, ſo woe vnto man, (more ſenſles than a ſtone) that cannot grone vnder the burden of his owne ſinne: rather adding ſinne vnto
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:184223:27"/>ſinne, as though it were no burden. Theſe creatures in their kinde, deſire after this great day: as for the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, theef, murderer of bodies or ſouls, or both; they and all their compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of darknes, deſire there may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come ſuch a day. The Atheiſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not that there will be ſuch a day: as for them, they ſhal need none other to teſtifie againſt them, than ſtocks, ſtones, oxen, aſſes, neerer God than they are. The conſideration of whoſe blindnes &amp; inſenſibilitie, cauſeth the Lord ſometimes to turne away from men, and crie out,
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 1.2.3</note> 
               <hi>Heare oh Heauens, and hearken oh Earth:</hi> juſtifying the Ox and Aſſe before them. Againſt ſuch, the Lord will call the Heavens aboue, and the Earth to judge, <hi>Pſalm. 50.4.</hi> as being perſons vnworthie to be judged by any, but inſenſible and vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creatures: becauſe ſuch Atheiſts are vnreaſonable and ſenſles.</p>
            <p>If the Heavens &amp; the earth (whome I ſee not to be acceſſarie to Satan and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:184223:28"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> his ſin, except becauſe <hi>the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> might be made of the heavens na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as <hi>Adam</hi> of the earthlie, and ſo the lumps ſhould ſuffer with the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures</hi> formed out of them, being once apoſtate: If the heavens &amp; the earth role away, and giue place at the appearance of our Lord, how ſhal wicked ſinfull man, author of his own and their miſerie, how ſhal he appeare before him that ſitteth vpon the <hi>white</hi> throane, from whome ſhall proceede nothing but pure judgement and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice? For in the daye of this fire, the Iudge ſhall appeare in vnſpeakable glorie: his garment as white as ſnow, his throane a fiery flame, a ſtreame of fire iſſuing before him, and thouſands of Angels round about him. Oh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued brethren, this ſhall be the great day of deliverance, for the Iudge ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to take vengeance on corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to glorifie ſinceritie and righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>If any enquire, <hi>Whether the creatures
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:184223:28"/>ſhall be delivered from their corruption, before man have received his full and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall doome in the fleſh?</hi> I anſwere, that point ſeemeth to me not very plaine from holy writ: yet by ſome reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conjecture, I eaſilie condiſcend to this: vz. <hi>That the Creatures ſhall firſt bee looſed from corruption.</hi> Firſt, becauſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man was) the creatures were exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, and that
<note n="*" place="margin">Geneſ. 1.</note> good every one of them. As they were created for mans vſe, ſo, ELOHIM wold not bring man into the waſt world (as into an emptie houſe) but firſt furniſhed the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie manſion of the world with al ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, and then brought man into the pallace of the world (and the moſt pleaſant chamber therein, <hi>Eden</hi>) that therein he might be exerciſed. Nowe when as the creatures ſhal be reſtored to their former libertie, I ſee not to what end, but that the ſame may (as in the order of firſt creation) be firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, and then manifeſted to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde in the glorious act of judgment,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:184223:29"/>for the letting of him ſee, howe good and glorious all thinges were, before they were attainted, and corrupted through mans ſin. And this may well be a preparation to the judgement or generall Seſſion of Chriſt Ieſus. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeemeth this to bee contrary to bleſſed <hi>Iohn</hi> his words, where he ſaith,
<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 20.11. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>I ſawe a great white throne, and one ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereon, from whoſe face fled avvay the Earth and Heauen:</hi> after which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing place of the corruptible heavens and the earth, he introduceth the dead and the opening of the books of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And if the
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>newe Heauens and new Earth,</hi> wherein Righteouſnes ſhal dwell, be the Heavens and the Earth then reſtored: then ſo much the more plaine it is, <hi>That all the creatures vnder degree of reaſon</hi> (and Angels and men are onely creatures <hi>Reaſonable) ſhall be looſed from their bondage &amp; corruption,</hi> (corruption giving place to him that ſitteth on the throne) and then be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (as it were) to giue in verdict with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:184223:29"/>the Faithfull that haue vſed them ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlie, righteouſlie: as alſo to witnes againſt the wicked that vſed them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperatlie, vnholilie, to the diſhonor of the Creator. Secondly, I am rather induced to thinke, that before all men haue received full and finall doome, they ſhall ſee the other creatures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to libertie, as for the animating and lifting vp of the heades of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: ſo, (and that more ſpecially) for the tormenting of the heartes of the <hi>Reprobate:</hi> who having ſeene, <hi>the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures reſtored and beautified,</hi> ſhall then vpon the books opening, be not onely driven from the ſweet <hi>behold</hi> of Ieſus,
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 1.5.</note> from the glorious Aſſemblie of the Saintes, but alſo from enjoying (ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the very ſight) of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent creatures. If any demaund, <hi>vvhat ſhall become of theſe Creatures after once they be delivered from corruption &amp; bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage?</hi> I anſwer, repaire vnto me the day after Doomeſ-day, and then I will tell thee. In the meane time, I am ſure that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:184223:30"/>nothing <hi>ſhall be,</hi> which ſhall not bring delight and glory vnto the ſonnes and daughters of God. Let curious que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions therfore ceaſe, and ſtudy rather how in that day thou maieſt be found blameles, and to <hi>Iehovah</hi> acceptable. Awake oh ye fooliſh virgins, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens are ready to run on a heape: the elements about thee to melt; the earth vnder thee to burne: and the Iudge of all fleſh is comming in cloudes, maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and power. Heark, hark, the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet calling vnto judgment: the Angels readie preſt to gather the harveſt: the graue, ſeas, and hell giving vp all: for all muſt preſently to Iudgment.</p>
            <p>The Iudge is ſet, thouſands of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels about his fiery throne: Satan and his black Guarde, come plodding to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Throane, as a Beare to the ſtake. The glorious Martyrs and all the faithfull, come flying towards the Iudg, with the wings of an Eagle, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<note n="*" place="margin">Saue I pray thee.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſanna, hoſanna, bleſſed is he that commeth in the name of</hi> IEHOVAH, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:184223:30"/>in the higheſt.</hi> As for the <hi>Beaſte, falſe Prophet, their marked people, and all workers &amp; lovers of iniquitie,</hi> me thinks I ſee them pulling back, but the decree of God whipping them all forwarde. Seduced People crye to the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Couer vs oh Father, from the wrath of him that ſitteth on the Throne:</hi> but he replieth, <hi>Aes me, Aes me, I am vnable to hide my ſelfe.</hi> One crieth, <hi>Oh King, oh Queene, ſaue me:</hi> but they anſwere, <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed ſubiects, we are not able to ſaue our ſelues:</hi> They replye, <hi>Oh, your fearefull Lawes and tyrannie, haue cauſed vs to vvorſhip God after a humaine, carnall, &amp; fooliſh manner.</hi> Oh, oh, (ſay Kings and Queenes againe) <hi>we are therefore accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and you condemned.</hi> Me thinks I ſee the Murtherer with a bloody ſword in his hand, and the ſouls of the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſlaughtered crying, <hi>Oh God our Avenger, now iudge thou betweene vs and that Murtherer:</hi> and the Murtherer, me thinks I heare him cry, <hi>Nowe I ſee theſe I perſecuted had in honour, but I the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:184223:31"/>vnable to beholde them in the face, againſt vvhome, I heretofore did harden my heart &amp; flint my face: oh that I might be killed to die, but I muſt liue ever to die.</hi> While thus their conſciences debate their falſe worſhippe, adulteries, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, thefts, blaſphemies, pride, &amp;c. the Lord commandeth all to appeare <hi>Coram.</hi> As by the Lords word,
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Let it be,</hi> every creature at firſt was formed, ſo, at one word, all appeare before the glorious Iudge and innumerable ſight of Angels.</p>
            <p>If the Iſraelites trembled at the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Lawe, howe ſhall Law-les people now tremble at the execution of the Law? Now
<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 1.7.</note> every eie ſhall ſee him, even they which haue pearced the Chriſt thorough, and all kinreds of the Earth ſhall lament before him: Al the earth encompaſſing the face of the Tribun all ſeate, the bookes (even every conſcience) ſhall be laide open. Every ſoule ſhall be naked to his eies, that ſeeth the ſecrets of the heart, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:184223:31"/>(as it were) in the tables of the ſoule ſhall every vnrepentant ſinne be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: Oh the ſecret murders, thefts, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſes, wicked counſells againſt Chriſts Church, that then ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to all the world, in ſomuch as one running by may reade them. In the face of <hi>Iudas</hi> his ſoule ſhal be written, <hi>I haue betrayed innocent blood:</hi> In the face of <hi>Pilate</hi> ſhall bee written, <hi>I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the innocent for pleaſing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> In the faces of <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Nimrod, We haue loued hunting, but neglected ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi> In the portall of <hi>Chams</hi> conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhal be printed: <hi>I reioyced to ſee the corrector of ſinne overtaken with ſin: and therefore publiſhed it to my brethren, that they togither with me, might for ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, make his nakednes a reaſon of our not hearing nor bearing his corrections: as vn fit to rule vs, that firſt could not rule him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: therefore iuſt that now my nakednes be laid open before God, Angels, and men.</hi> In the Conſcience of <hi>Herod,</hi> ſhall bee drawne as it were, in great text letters,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:184223:32"/>
               <hi>I vſed not my guifts to the praiſe of God the giuer, but laboured thereby to catch praiſe vnto my ſelfe:</hi> In <hi>Balaam</hi> and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry covetous teacher his face ſhall be written, <hi>I preached for pelfe:</hi> but then, <hi>Oh woe,</hi> vnto the dumbe Miniſter: for his Conſcience ſhall thus indite him: <hi>Balaam was better than I, for though hee did all for gold, yet he preached: as for me, I occupied a feeders roome, and had a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders fee, but I fed not the people, by divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the vvord, and cauſing them to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the holy myſterie.</hi> Then ſhall the wicked Kinges, Queenes, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, haue graven deeply in the face of their accuſing conſcience: <hi>We haue kept out the kingdome of Chriſt, for plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Religion drawn out of our politicks, an</hi> Ethelo threskia <hi>or Wil-worſhip,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.22.23.</note> 
               <hi>vvhich had indeede a ſhewe of wiſedome,</hi> but was not according vnto the wiſedome of God. In a word, then ſhall every man his conſcience carrie his owne indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his ſin hanging before the door of his Conſcience, as doeth the Iuie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:184223:32"/>before the wine-ſeller: and hee that knowes not this, knows leſſe than did the Heathen Philoſopher <hi>Plato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the conſciences of the <hi>Elect,</hi> they ſhall all in this great day be clear from clamour and accuſation, every one having written in his conſcience, (as had <hi>Paule</hi>)
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>I knowe nothing by my ſelfe:</hi> and this puritie of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence falleth out, by reaſon that they here in this life diſclaimed their ſinns for baſtardly fruites, and by the teares of vnfained ſorrowe, did waſh their conſciences, the Lord therewithall putting all their ſinnes out of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance; and ſo are they by the
<note n="*" place="margin">Col. 1.28.</note> Lords Prophets and preachers, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented perfect in Chriſt leſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſciences of all this multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 2.15.16.</note> either <hi>accuſing</hi> or <hi>excuſing</hi> one another, (in this great daye, wherein God ſhal judge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Chriſt, and that according to the Goſpell) immediately therevpon, ſhall the conſcience excuſing be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:184223:33"/>on the right hand: but the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences accuſing vpon the left hand of the Iudge.</p>
            <p>Then vnto his recovered ſheep ſhall Chriſt ſay,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.34, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>I vvas an hungred, and yee gaue me meat: I thirſted, and ye gaue me drink. I was a ſtranger and ye lodged me: being naked ye clothed me: I vvas ſicke, and ye viſited me: I vvas in priſon and ye came vnto me:</hi> But they vnwilling to aſſume any thing to themſelues, ſhall replie, <hi>When did vve ſo vnto thee?</hi> to whome he ſhall anſwer: <hi>hauing done it vnto one of the leaſt of my bretheren, yee haue done it vnto me. Therefore</hi> (or, in aſmuch as all may ſee your faith was no dead faith) <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> (even bleſſed
<note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world) <hi>inherit ye the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you before the Worlds foundation;</hi> even before ye could doe good or evill. Wherevpon, the glory of God encompaſſeth them, and not only that, but they are filled with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and are made
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>like vnto Chriſt</hi> (in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:184223:33"/>
               <hi>qualitie,</hi> though not in <hi>quantitie) ſeeing him as he is:</hi> a glory beyond the conceit of man. And therefore oh my ſoule, here glut thee, and be thou raviſhed in the ſpirite (as was IOHN in <hi>Paetmos</hi>) and bee content to contemplate that which neither thy hand can ſet down; thy tongue vtter, nor yet thy ſelf look towards, vntill thy fleſh by ſtrength of Gods ſpirit, be humbled to the Earth, &amp; ly as dead, for giving further ſcope vnto the inner man. Neither hauing contemplated profoundlie in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſhall thou attaine to the leaſt peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, or jod of that glory: a glory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the glittering ſhine of the Sun, Moone, ſtarres: for this muſt be end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, as Chriſt himſelfe is endles.</p>
            <p>But vnto the goatiſh multitude and hypocriticall tares, he ſhall ſay: <hi>I vvas an hungred and ye gaue me no meate: I thirſted, and ye gaue me no drink: I vvas a ſtranger, and ye lodged me not: naked, and ye clothed me not: ſick and in priſon, but ye viſited me not:</hi> But as willing to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:184223:34"/>cover their vnworking faith, they ſhal ſay: <hi>When did we ſee thee and not releeue thee?</hi> The judge ſhall anſwere: <hi>Verely I ſay vnto you, in as much as yee did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me. Depart therefore from me ye curſed, into everlaſting fire, which is prepared for the Deuill and his Angels.</hi> Herevpon the Devils &amp; all workers of iniquitie ſhall go into everlaſting paine: as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer into life everlaſting. Oh the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible noiſe and roarings of devils and men at this departure to the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les pit, where the worme (worſe than a ſnake or viper) ſhall gnawe every of them to the death, &amp; yet not die. The Lord his flayle and whippe of Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhall nowe bruiſe and laſhe them more fiercely, then doth <hi>Iehouahs</hi> flayl the Heathen, in the valley of <hi>Iehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat.</hi> for the firſt, is but a part; but this, the fulnes of his wrath.</p>
            <p>But as the <hi>ſhritchings</hi> &amp; howlings of the latter ſhall be immeaſurable: ſo the <hi>Singings</hi> of the former, togeather
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:184223:34"/>with the glorious Angels, ſhall be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable heavenly, even a melody vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable. The Devil departeth with his myſticall black body, and helliſh corporation. Chriſt ariſeth togither with his glorious and myſticall body, (
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.24.28.</note> nowe all his adverſaries trampled vnder his feete) and delivereth vp the kingdome to God the Father: hee and his body thence ſtanding ſubject vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that did ſubdue all things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, that <hi>God may be all in all.</hi> Firſt, God and Chriſt is all one: ſecondly, Chriſt and the faithful are all one: laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Father, the Son, and the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are all one: according to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour his petition: <hi>Iohn. 17.20.21. &amp;c.</hi> And all this falleth out after an vnvtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable manner: God firſt abaſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by aſſuming our nature: and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, lifting vs vp vnſpeakable high, that ſo being like Chriſt, wee may beholde the glory of the Father, and bee one with God. Neither thenceforth can the myſticall members of Chriſt fall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:184223:35"/>away from their myſticall head, more than Chriſt from his head the Father; and the Father from himſelfe. Oh fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie fleſh, filthie lumpiſh fleſh, that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth not this myſticall <hi>Vnion,</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Com-vnion:</hi> God (as it were) tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlated into man, and man into God: the Creator into a creature; and the creature into the Creator. Dy, dy, oh my fleſh, and be thou more and more vivified oh my ſpirit, that I may be lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp beyond my ſelfe, to ſee my ſelfe greater than my ſelfe. Oh miſerable wretch I am, to ſin againſt this God, mercifull God, that by his vncompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable wiſedome hath provided, that I (a baſe worme) ſhould become one with God.</p>
            <p>Oh my beloved brethren and ſiſters of <hi>England,</hi> (as alſo, oh yee people of other Nations,) <hi>Conſidering all theſe things</hi> (not onely, the conſumption of all by fire, but eſpecially the <hi>Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> and <hi>Reiecting</hi> of ſoules immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie after) <hi>vvhat maner of perſons</hi> (ſay I
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:184223:35"/>with <hi>Peter) ought ye to be in holy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and godlines?</hi> If the corruptible Heavens, elements, earth &amp; the works therein, ſhal be vnable in their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible eſtate to apeare before that great and incorruptible Iudge: how had ye neede while it is called <hi>To day,</hi> to caſt aſide all filthineſſe and ſuperfluitie of wickednes; that ſo you may with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſtand before that white Throne? as though the Apoſtle woulde ſay, do not your Conſciences beare witnes, that ye had neede to liue in pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation and godlineſſe? and if your conſciences do teſtifie, that much pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and holineſſe is required, at the handes of thoſe that ſhal come before that Iudge: then (leſt your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences doe condemne you in that great day) do labour more in holines of converſation towards man; as alſo that ſuch outward converſation, may proceede from an heart, inwardly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with godlines, The Apoſtle ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it for graunted, that every mans
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:184223:36"/>conſcience will make ſuch anſwer to his demaund, doth ſecretly even in the ſame demaund, exhort vnto holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation and godlines. In deede, no exhortation can in better time be vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, then when the conſcience is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed. And oh thou Atheiſt, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou be, tel me if theſe things ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lye not at the doore of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, (as did
<note n="*" place="margin">Geneſ. 4.7</note> 
               <hi>Cains</hi> ſin at his door) and giue thee a twitch &amp; bloody nip, ſnarling at the banket of thy ſinne, as a Dogge vnder the table? Oh thou A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, that corroding of thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, wil prooue the ſculpture and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauement of thy ſin in thy ſoule, that ſo it may be viſible to the eies of al the world, in the great &amp; generall doome. Awake therefore, oh Atheiſt, and all ye lovers of iniquitie, and
<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
               <hi>followe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, vvithout vvhich, no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> See him without holineſſe they may, as Satan, the ſheepherd of hell and his goats ſhall ſee him, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a fearefull and terrible Iudge; every
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:184223:36"/>word of whoſe mouth, ſhall wounde them as an envenomed arrowe: but ſee the Lord to their comfort (as ſhall lovers of holines) they never ſnall; and therefore (as our Saviour ſaith)
<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 5.8</note> 
               <hi>The pure in heart are bleſſed, for they ſhall ſee God:</hi> as for the impure hearted, they (by the nature of contraries) are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, for they ſhall ſee the Devill.</p>
            <p>Be not deceived, God will not bee mocked; as thou ſowes, thou ſhalt reape. If thou reply, Though I liue in vncleanneſſe, Idolatrie, witchcraft, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, debate, emulations, wrath, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, ſeditions, hereſies, envie, murthers, drunkennes, gluttonie, and ſuch like, yet I hope to be ſaved: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and not I, but PAVL: <hi>They which do ſuch things ſhall not inherite the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, Gal. 5.21.</hi> Chriſt will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent man before his Father, as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelfe: but
<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> hee preſented himſelfe without falt, therefore he wil preſent man without falt. If thou ſaieſt, <hi>I hope</hi> he will preſent me as a ſonne to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:184223:37"/>God: <hi>Iohn</hi> maketh this anſwer:
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Iohn 3.3</note> 
               <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that hath this Hope, purifieth himſelfe, even as hee is pure.</hi> Purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on goeth before ſalvation: the putting off of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> with his deceiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able luſtes, before the newe <hi>Adam</hi> can be put on with his holines and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes: before Chriſt can exalt thee, <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt humble thee: before that Chriſts works be imputed thine, thou muſt forſake the works that are thine: before God adopt thee his Son, thou muſt diſclame the devill, the father of thy corrupt nature: and if thou wilt haue Chriſt to be thy King, thou muſt covenant holy obedience due to that King. The Heavens are pure in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thee, yet the Heavenly Spheres and glittering Starres muſt giue place to the brightneſſe of his Throne: howe much more muſt thy damnable corruption be caſt awaye, except thou, togither with thy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption will be for ever caſt away?</p>
            <p>Come wee but before an earthlie
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:184223:37"/>King, Queene: Lord, oh howe we will trick vp our attire, make bright our countenance, and ſtudy to place our wordes in order: and all this, why do we? becauſe forſooth, wee muſt come before a noble man, a noble woman. But howe prepare we for meeting of the Lord of Lords, in the clowds, who ſhall come with the
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 15 52. Matth. 24.</note> 
               <hi>ſound of a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> his Angels marching before, to gather togither his Elect from one wind vnto another? how are wee fitted with ſpirituall garments? ſhall wee be clad with the workes of darknes? with what face, wil we look him in the face? harlots faces, theeuiſh faces, murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring faces, faces puft vppe with pride, theſe will not ſerue the turne. With what words will we greet the judge of all the world? He ſaith, we ſhal giue an accompt of all our
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 12.36</note> 
               <hi>Idle vvords,</hi> and dare wee meete him with vnſavourie ſpeaches and rotten words? Away, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with ſuch care to pleaſe men, and in the meane time careleſſe to pleaſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:184223:38"/>God, careles how Chriſt find vs occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, careles how to come before his judgement ſeate. The Heavens ſhall giue place, but man will ſtand ſtill in the way of ſinners: the Elements ſhall melt; but mans heart will not melte more than an Adamant: the earth ſhal willinglie permit the fire to conſume his corruption, but man will not let the fire of God (his ſpirite) burne vp and conſume his corrupt nature, and vnprofitable luſtes: The Devils at the rememberance of this great day doe tremble: but man can heare of the <hi>Great day,</hi> the <hi>Fire</hi> of that day, the <hi>iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of that day, and never be ſtirred in his ſoul. Oh miſerable man, and ten times more ſtupid than any creature, ſtriue and contend to feare before the Iudge of al the Earth, ſtudying holines and righteouſnes, without which thou ſhalt never ſee God. Let (now at laſt) thy ſtony heart guſh out teares (as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Nomb. 20 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Rock</hi> guſhed out waters) &amp; bath thy ſoul in them contrite teares,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:184223:38"/>as in another Baptiſme: and riſe vppe from thy earthly waies (as
<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> ſmit downe, roſe from the Earth) and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after (ſhaking the ſcales of naturall blindnes from thy eies) go and learne to be holy as our head is holy, that ſo thou
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet. 3.14</note> 
               <hi>maieſt be found of him, in Peace, without ſpot and blameles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mount <hi>Sinaj,</hi> vpon the promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy law, was al on ſmoke; the ſmoke aſcending as the ſmoke of a fornace, and the mountaine trembled exceedingly: but in this great daye of the Lord, all the mountaines of the world, all vallies, high thinges, lowe things, ſhall not onely ſmoke, but frye in a conſuming flame. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> trembled at the firſt, and ſhall not wee tremble at the ſecond? The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> durſt not approch <hi>Sinaj,</hi> before they were
<note n="*" place="margin">Exo. 19.14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> ſanctified by <hi>Moſes:</hi> and dare we approach the great day of doome, (what time the breach of the Law ſhal be puniſhed in the lake of ſcortching brimſtone and vnquenchable fire) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:184223:39"/>we be ſanctified by Chriſt Ieſus? They durſt not come neere the Hill with vnwaſhen clothes, but wee think to ſtand before Chriſt his pure throne of Iudgment, and that with vnwaſhen hands, vnwaſhen hearts; where as no one ſhall appeare (without confuſion of face) that firſt haue not
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>made their Robes vvhite in the blood of the Lamb.</hi> I ſay not, in his owne workes; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay againe, <hi>in the blood of the Lambe.</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therefore is he that watcheth and keepeth his (ſpirituall) garments, leaſt (at his ſodaine comming) he walk na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: and men (ey, and Angels) ſee his filthines. If thou ſhame not now at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy converſation and vngodlines; in that great daye, an helliſh ſhame ſhall cover thy face, and horrour of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall confound thee. If the Devill ſhal not then claime thee for his own, do here ſhake of his livery cote of <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holines,</hi> and teare of his cognizance of <hi>vngodlines:</hi> but if thou here will carrie his vnholy brand in thy fore-heade,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:184223:39"/>hand, and hart, then togither with thy black Lord, exſpect to be committed to the
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 21.8.</note> 
               <hi>Lake vvhich burneth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that great day, wicked <hi>Cain</hi> and his Citie: <hi>Nimrod</hi> &amp; his bloodhounds: wicked <hi>Saule</hi> and his deſperate Iaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: <hi>Balaam</hi> and his bribe: the Vſurer and his money-bagges ſhal be parted: Theuiſh <hi>Achan</hi> and his wedg of golde, ſhal be ſundred: the harlot and whore, divorced: The murderer, and his bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow-blade: the Idolater, &amp; his ſhryne: the dronken <hi>Nabal</hi> and his tipling cup: the Merchant, and his falſe meaſure: the Courtier, and his ſofte raiment: <hi>Nebuchadnezzer,</hi> and his pallatial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: the Glutton, and his belching banquet: the mad dauncer, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, in that great daye they ſhall ſhake hands and never meet more. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all which and more terrible than that, muſt and ſhall bee effected, what manner of perſons ſhoulde Kings and Queenes be? what maner of perſons,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:184223:40"/>had rich men need to be? what maner of perſons, had Prophets neede to be? what maner of men and weomen, had wee all neede to be, in holines of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and godlines? That when <hi>Cain</hi> ſhall roare for his murder: <hi>Cham</hi> for not covering his fathers nakednes: <hi>Eſau</hi> for his miſpent time, &amp; ſcorning ſacramentall ſignes: <hi>Saul</hi> for his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution: the falſe Prophet for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Peace</hi> to men, when men were not at peace with God, <hi>Shechem,</hi> for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing <hi>Dinah: Alexander</hi> the Copper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, for reſiſting <hi>Paul:</hi> That when <hi>Demas</hi> ſhall wring his handes for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from preaching the Goſpell, to liue as a Farmer and grazier: that when proude <hi>Diotrephes</hi> ſhall curſe himſelfe for pratling and playing the buſy-body againſt the Saintes; to the end, that then we may boldly hold vp our heads, in the teſtimonie of a good conſcience, let vs nowe ſo liue, as wee may not feare preſently to die. Let vs nowe ſtudy ſo to die, as wee may not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:184223:40"/>feare preſently to make appearance before that glorious Iudge, and al the glorious Armie of Heaven. So liued not the earthly minded Prophet, who in the teſtimonie of a bad conſcience, cryed:
<note place="margin">Nomb. 23.10.</note> 
               <hi>Oh that I might die the death of the Righteous, and that my laſt end might be like his.</hi> But ſo lived the humble poor Apoſtle, who in the teſtimonie of a good conſcience, cryed: <hi>I deſire to bee diſſolued and to be with Chriſt.</hi> So lived good <hi>Simeon,</hi> who could ſay, <hi>Lord now thou letteſt thy ſervant depart in peace:</hi> And ſo muſt every profeſſor of Chriſt liue, as when hee heareth Chriſt ſay,
<note n="*" place="margin">Reu. 22.20</note> 
               <hi>Surely I come quickly:</hi> he with longing ſoule may anſwere, <hi>Amen: even ſo, Come Lord Ieſus, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Sic vivamus ἐν τῷ κοσμω,</l>
               <l>Vt ne ſimus ἐκ τοῦ κοσμοῦ.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184223:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184223:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
